Hello, I'm your host David Barnard and
with me today RevenueCat CEO Jacob
Eiding. Our guest today is Phil Carter,
an independent growth advisor and angel
investor helping consumer subscription
companies. Phil spent the last decade as
a VC and product leader at companies
like Fair, Quizlet, and Ibotta. On the
podcast, we talk with Phil about his
subscription value loop framework, what
it means to create robust value for
customers, and why AB testing shouldn't
be your first step in price
optimization.
Phil, thanks so much for joining us on
the podcast today. It's good to be here.
Thanks for having me. And Jacob, always
nice to chat with you. I'm extremely
excited to be here with you today,
David. So Phil, you have a ton of
experience working with subscription
apps. You've been doing consulting for a
while now working with a bunch of great
apps. As we dive into some of your
frameworks and other things, I know a
lot of those were developed in your time
at Quizlet, so let's kick it off talking
about Quizlet and how you ended up
working there. Yeah, sure. So I found my
way to Quizlet through a bit of a
circuitous route. I started my career
out of college as a consultant as many
of us do, but then pretty quickly
discovered tech in the Bay Area and was
the first employee at a car sharing app
called Wheels. It was a pretty cool
product. We had the first in-car device
where you could sound the horn, lock and
unlock the vehicle, find it on your
iPhone and Android if you were under
reservation. And so that was a cool
product and then ended up going to
business school, spent a few years in
venture capital doing early stage
consumer mobile investing. And so that's
how I found my way to consumer tech
specifically, which you know, it goes in
ebbs and flows. There are a lot of
people out there who spend their whole
careers in B2B, but I was attracted to
technology for the impact it can have on
everyday people's lives. And so spent a
few years in venture capital and then
I'd met my wife Ashley in business
school and we wanted to be closer to
family in the great outdoors. So we
packed all of our belongings up into our
Subaru in 2015, drove across country to
Colorado.
And I've been here ever since as a
product and growth leader for a few
companies out here. Cool. So then what
attracted you to working at Quizlet? I
know there was some like specific
aspects of the product that seemed to
gel with you. So why Quizlet? Yeah, so
the funny story about Quizlet is I'd
actually never heard of the company at
the time and I was briefly embarrassed
about that until I found out that a lot
of other people hadn't heard of it
either. It was like one of these really
well-kept secrets where high school and
college students in the US have been
using Quizlet for over a decade. I
wasn't quite in the age demographic to
where it was instrumental tool for me
personally. So I had a recruiter reach
out in 2018 and mentioned this company
Quizlet that was starting a Denver
office. And at the time I'd been working
at Ibotta, I'd been leading core product
team there, but I found that I really
loved growth and specifically
product-driven growth, things like
onboarding, SEO, conversion
optimization, conversion. And so when I
heard about Quizlet, it just felt like
the perfect alignment of a really
interesting product, a great mission
that was really making people's lives
better, and then a great business model.
Like when I looked at the unit economics
as part of my interview process there,
the combination of really low-cost
organic user acquisition through word of
mouth and SEO combined with the
recurring revenue that you get from a
subscription business was really
compelling to me. So I ended up taking
the job to go start Quizlet's growth
team and I went home for the holidays
that year and told my cousins I was
joining this startup called Quizlet and
they were like, "Yeah, of course we know
Quizlet, we've been using it for years."
Yeah, I'm sure this is something you've
seen in patterns now, but this low cost
of acquisition. There's always like
something with the great subscription
apps like Duolingo, I think it was the
same way. There's something about them
that makes their CAC really low. And
Quizlet, I feel like students in that
community, they have high needs, like
specific needs, and they're very viral,
right? So they're like communicated a
ton. And that changes everything. But it
struck me the I don't know if this is
irony or whatever this is, but that's
when you hire the growth team, right?
It's like bringing the growth team when
you have the good economics. That's the
company you want to come into. It's like
the company that doesn't need a growth
team. Then bring in the growth team,
right? And that's exactly what I was
going to say. So it's like they were
already growing, they had a lot of word
of mouth. What did they hire you to do
then? And what did you do at Quizlet?
Quizlet already had a few people who
were working on growth. And so they'd
been doing some sign-up optimization
work, things like user onboarding flows,
sign-up walls. And the company was
growing very nicely. And so it didn't
just make it a really compelling
opportunity, it also made my job much
easier getting things to the next level.
Where I really added value was getting
into the nuts and bolts of how Quizlet
had gotten to where it was and then how
we were going to replicate that growth
going forward. And more and more so
replicate that growth in international
markets where 95% of the global student
population lives outside the US. And so
that was a huge challenge for us. So one
of the first things I did in my first
few months there was
I talked to a lot of customers,
obviously. I spent a lot of time in the
weeds with the analytics team and
basically distilled down, "Okay,
Quizlet's been around for almost 15
years at that point, a lot of different
product features, lots of different user
segments, but like at the end of the
day, what's really driving growth for
this business?" And it turned out that
there were six key actions
and four core growth loops, SEO being
the most important one that was driving
a lot of the growth. And so then based
on that information, we built a
quantitative growth model around it. We
were able to more systematically drive
user and revenue growth from that point.
The quantitative growth model, this was
a thing I remember hearing about. It's
kind of the holy grail of how to build a
growth system, right? It's like you have
to have a model. What does that
practically mean? Like what is that? Is
that some machine learning thing? Like
what is that? I mean, the short answer
is it looks very different at every
company for good reason because you
can't just take one template and sort of
copy-paste and have it work for your
business. But what you're looking for is
the simplest possible model you can get
away with, call it the minimum viable
model, that really gets at the variables
that are most leveraged for driving your
business that are tied to those key user
actions. And so for Quizlet, we had
acquisition, retention, and monetization
assumptions built into the model. It was
about 100 variables and we broke it down
by students versus teachers and a couple
of other key variables. I won't go into
too much detail. It was simple enough
that it could be communicated across the
company and used to align people around
common ways of thinking about growth,
but complex enough that it could help
inform strategy and identify where the
biggest leverage points were. I remember
being in this position at Elevate and
being like, "What is like a model? Like
how do I make this? Like what? I need to
hire like somebody fancy to do some
fan-" And so it's like, "No, literally
just write the equation that equals
money." Right? Put money on one side
and then figure out the multiplication
problem and addition problem. Usually
it's linear algebra that goes in and
generates that money and that's your
model. And it's different like you said,
it's like, "Okay, well, we have teachers
generate some amount of something,
students generate another amount of
something multiplied by our conversion
rate, multiplied by this." I mean, I
have one for RevenueCat as well. Then
you just take partial derivatives,
right? You be like, "Okay, what's the
most effective variable to move today?
What are some strategies I can employ?"
And it just helps you to like hold the
business in your head in terms of like
the mechanics of it. And like I don't
know if you found this, but they're
always wrong. And that's the They're
always wrong. We
So So Reforge actually has a really
provocative statement, which our models
are useless, but the exercise of
modeling is absolutely necessary because
it forces you to really think through
the hardest questions. And then the
other thing is So there's two
components, right? There's the more
complex quantitative version of the
model, but the blueprint of the model is
basically just one image of the various
actions users are taking and the
compounding loops that forms that drives
user revenue growth. And in a lot of
cases, that ends up being equally
valuable because it just gets everybody
on the same page using the same language
and operating off of the same
assumption. The schematic for the
business. And you were talking about
alignment, right? You can start to like
be like, "All right, team X, this is the
part of the acyclic graph you're going
to be working on, right?" Or I guess it
is a cyclic graph in this case. This is
the like little loop you're going to be
working on. This is a loop you're going
to be working on, something like that.
So yeah, it's super useful. Yeah, one
other thing we did is we built the most
basic version of the model for the US
only, but then we replicated for other
international markets. So you could
literally put a country code into a
Python script and replicate the whole
thing for a target market in Europe or
South America or Asia. And that was cool
because it just let us look at how the
business was growing differently across
different regions. Yeah, you basically
can slice it, right? I'm sure you didn't
have that on day one. All right? You
probably had something more simple.
We did not. So in building this very
Quizlet specific model, I know you came
up with kind of like a broader framework
to think about subscription app growth.
So I'd love to dive into that now, the
subscription value loop. Tell me how
that work at Quizlet informed what you
now developed as the subscription value
loop and what it is. And then we'll dive
into all the specifics of the
subscription value loop. Yeah, sure.
Well, like so many of these stories, I'd
love to say that I had this all in my
head at the time.
I absolutely did not. So this was a
framework I actually developed more
recently as I've been starting this
growth advising business. But at the
time, the way it manifested was there
were two problems. One was coming out of
the model work, where are the biggest
bottlenecks in the business? And then
based on that, where the biggest
strategic opportunities we should be
focused on because as a product or
growth leader, you're always constrained
by people and by time, right? And so
you've got to find the highest leverage
initiative to be working on at any given
time and that's always a challenge. You
all have a lot of founders on your
podcast who are working at smaller apps,
but as you get to this sort of awkward
adolescent phase of a series B, series C
company, you're kind of figuring out,
"Okay, where does growth product fit in
versus core product versus growth
marketing?" And this was a challenge I
heard come up over and over again cuz I
would talk to my peers at other
companies. I'm like, "I'm figuring this
out for the first time. I haven't led a
growth product team prior to this. I was
working on core product at Ibotta. So
how are you thinking about this?" And I
just kept hearing the same challenges of
like we're stepping on marketing's toes
because life cycle marketing really
needs to work with onboarding. So how do
we coordinate on that? And we don't know
when core product should be taking the
lead versus growth product. And so I
started talking about this idea of value
creation versus value capture.
And working with the VP of product at
Quizlet around okay, how can we have
core product teams really focus on
creating core value for the users
with the primary metric being retention.
And then free up growth product to focus
on value capture as well as new user
onboarding and various things that sort
of connect users to that core value. So
this idea of value creation versus value
capture is where it all started and it
seemed to really resonate with my team
and with the executives at Quizlet. And
then as we started to adopt this
framework more and more, we also talked
to marketing about how can we best
coordinate on bringing more people into
Quizlet whether that be free users or
ultimately subscribers. And so that's
where the interim step of value delivery
came in. So this subscription value
loop, value creation, value delivery,
value capture. I think it is a really
great way to think about this kind of
like high-level model like we've been
talking about almost all businesses,
right?
Yeah, it's creation and capture. That's
the thing. Delivery's part of that as
well like distribution but creation and
capture is somewhat universal. Do you
have any concrete examples of how this
plays out? This has come up on a number
of your other podcast episodes. This
idea of you know in the early days of
the app stores that were no subscription
apps. It was all just pay to download,
pay to use. And then subscription apps
started to come along but it took a
little while for the best companies to
really figure out how to create this
compounding value engine. And the best
businesses ended up leapfrogging their
competitors in many cases because
they found
a really important need that was going
unmet or not sufficiently met. They
really invested a lot of their resources
in making that solution to that need as
good as it possible could be. But then
importantly
they were able to capture enough of that
value on the back end to reinvest into
the business and build that moat around
their core product advantage. And so one
of the examples that has come up on a
previous Sub Club episode is the example
of Spotify versus Pandora. Where Pandora
was the first mover in that space but
was more of an ad-driven model and that
was suboptimal for two reasons. One, it
wasn't the best user experience cuz you
would get interrupted all the time while
you were listening to your music. And
then two, they didn't have as much
profit density in their business model.
Their LTV CAC ratio I would guess. I
don't know. I never worked at Pandora
but I would guess it wasn't as strong as
it could have been had they had
Spotify's model. And so along comes
Spotify, they really go all in on the
subscription business model and they
find a way to really efficiently
reinvest that revenue back into the core
product experience. And then you can
look at the charts out there. I mean
they just closed the gap very quickly
and the rest is history. And then what
aspects of working day-to-day in a
subscription app do you feel like can be
best informed at a high level from this
subscription value loop? Yeah, well I
think where it gets interesting cuz your
point earlier Jacob, if you zoom out
enough, this framework applies to almost
any business, certainly any consumer
subscription app.
really. Yeah, it's capitalism.
I think what's different though about
consumer subscriptions even relative to
prosumer apps is they really have to
sell themselves because the LTVs on
consumer subscriptions are much lower
than enterprise SaaS or prosumer, right?
And so you need a really, really
efficient machine for this to work and
you need everybody at the company to
understand what their roles and
responsibilities are and how they fit
into the framework. I think where the
river hits the road is on the specific
prerequisites within each step that need
to be true for it to really be firing on
all cylinders and then what that means
in terms of initiatives that the team
works on and how they approach solving
problems. Let's dive in. I'm excited to
go through the nuts and bolts and like
details of each of these points in the
subscription value loop. So the first
one is value creation. We've kind of
talked at a very high level but what is
in this framework, what is value
creation? So value creation is likely
the most important step, right? Because
if you don't have a product that people
really want then nothing else matters.
And so it really comes down to what I'm
calling the four Rs within the
framework. So is it robust? Are you
delivering value rapidly? Is it
repeatable value? And then is it
remarkable enough that people are going
to talk about it and ultimately build a
community around it.
And so we can go through those one by
one but the first is robust which is
really a measure of do you have a value
promise that is solving a real pain
point for customers? And do you have
strong product market fit? And so one of
the things that I look at when I'm
thinking about this part of value
creation is there's a 40% test that Sean
Ellis developed. He was the first
marketer at Dropbox. And it's a very
simple test. You just ask your customers
if you were no longer able to use this
product today, how disappointed would
you be? Very disappointed, somewhat
disappointed or not disappointed. He
realized over time after working with
enough companies and talking to enough
customers that the golden benchmark was
40%. You needed 40% of your customers to
say that they would be very disappointed
if they could no longer use your product
to really say you had strong product
market fit. And you can also sub-segment
that. So you can look at it globally
across all of your users but you can
also peel the onion back and look at
smaller segments. And so one of the
things that I think Superhuman actually
pioneered this idea but a lot of other
companies have followed it is product
market fit can be very binary. You hear
people talk about well you know product
market fit when you see it because
everything just gets easier. But that's
not very actionable and it can feel very
lonely as a founder of a new company
who's like trying to figure out well,
how far away are we from product market
fit? It's like a combustion process that
is like exothermic versus endothermic.
If your process takes energy, you just
you push it it stops. You push it it
stops. You push it it stops. I always
think about it and that's why it's
binary is like eventually the
combustion, the reaction, whatever
chemistry magic you're making becomes
exothermic. It can actually like release
energy and that's you come above this
line somewhere and then that's where you
get that perception I believe. Then
everything just starts to run away. If
it has enough fuel, it can potentially
go forever, right?
Then you start feeding the fuel not
pushing it yourself. Yeah. Yeah,
exactly. The problem is that you're
about to highlight is that you don't
know if you're one iteration or a
thousand iterations away from tripping
into that boundary. Unfortunately, it's
not as predictive as say like chemistry
is, right? Yeah, no that's right and I
love the car analogy. I know Lenny has
used it and it's one that I often think
about as a growth leader. But that's
right. You want to know are we even
building the right car? So where the 40%
test is so helpful is you can say okay,
are we at 20% of our customers very
disappointed? Are we at 30%? Are we at
40%? And then not many companies do this
but if you're really systematic about
it, you can actually create an objective
function and sort of work your way over
the line. And so Rahul Vohra who's the
founder and CEO at Superhuman has this
great blog post where he talks about how
Superhuman did this in the early days.
They were looking for a way to measure
product market fit. He found Sean Ellis.
They did the 40% test and they found out
that they were below the line but maybe
not as below the line as they would have
thought. And then they went through this
iterative process where they basically
looked at which segments of their users
had the highest propensity to say they
would be very disappointed and they
re-segmented the data and that got them
a little bit closer. And then they went
and talked to those users and they said
well what would it take for you to be
more delighted by this product, more
willing to pay for it? And by doing
that, they were able to really hone
around the nucleus of their highest
intent users and develop a product
roadmap that filled those gaps. And very
quickly, he goes into detail in the blog
post but very quickly that allowed them
to get past that 40% threshold and learn
a lot along the way that helped them
later on as they were scaling the
business. Would you do that 40% test at
a feature level too to like understand
which features specifically are driving
that delight versus like at a higher
level overall product level? It's an
interesting question and I don't want to
say you couldn't do that but I don't
think it's the right approach because
the best products have a one plus one
equals three effect, right? The whole is
greater than the sum of its parts. And
so I think what you want to segment on
is the user persona and not the feature.
There are other tools that can allow you
to isolate the value of individual
features which is really important.
Yeah, it is the thing you probably run
into statistical issues or depending on
your user base size. I think that's one
thing that is fraught a little bit in
these surveys is like depending on who
you're sampling and it can really vary.
That same segmentation question but in
generally like who are you asking? Is it
everybody who ever signed up? Is it
everybody who ever hit your web page? Or
is it everybody who ever like actually
uses the product, right? I think in some
arguments, everybody who uses the
product is pretty good cuz if anybody's
using the product, you've got product
market fit for somebody. How deep is it
and stuff like that? I think you need to
also use these in conjunctions with some
of the other classic product market fit
usage statistics like retention,
whatever makes sense for your product.
If it's a consumer product, day one, day
seven. If that's a SaaS product, it's
probably something a little bit
different. Cuz like you were saying,
Sean said 40%. Yeah.
You know, like what's the what's the
science behind it? You know, kind of
works. And I do agree. I have seen
people use this and it gives you a good
directionality but that's a lot of this
stuff. It's all very directional. Well,
none of these are silver bullets. It's
using them in tandem where I think you
get the magic. Yeah. And before we move
on from robust, it was a perfect thing
to kick off the whole subscription value
loop on robustness because I do think
that's missing from so many apps who
think it's a growth problem, it's a
marketing problem, it's a retention
problem, it's a whatever problem they
think it is. At the core, it's just so
easy to build an app. You said this.
It's easy to build an app but it's hard
to stand out. And robustness is where it
just has to be a good product. Like
people actually have to care. People
actually have to get value from it. Like
it has to be something real to build a
good business on top of and I do see a
lot of apps and I mean there's different
niches like a knitting app is a great
example of that. Like I don't care about
knitting but for some segment of the
population like a knitting app is
amazing and valuable. But whatever it is
it's like you just have to actually
create value and so robust while I know
you use that word to fit into the four
R's of value creation just a little bit
awkward as it
consultant. I've got to make a pivot.
But that foundation of just value
creation I think just is so important.
Anything else you wanted to talk about
on the value creation robustness side of
things before we move on to the other
R's in value creation. Completely agree
with what you just said. This is the
first step for a reason. If you don't
have a robust value promise nothing else
matters. The only other thing I would
say is we talked about finding initial
product market fit but this can also be
really important for companies that have
already found product market fit but are
trying to expand that product market
fit. And so a couple examples of this
that come to mind. I was at Quizlet
during the time when they acquired
Slater which ended up becoming their
textbook explanations tool. And so
that's a great example of Quizlet up
until that point had historically been
focused on repetition-based learning and
preparing for exams. The acquisition of
Slater and standing up Quizlet
explanations really helped them move
into the homework help and getting
unstuck problem space and so that's a
perfect example of if you would looked
at a segment of users they would have
probably told you like this is a need we
wish Quizlet had and that filled the
gap. And then I've been working with a
number of subscription companies more
recently as part of my advising work and
one of the companies is called Matter.
It's kind of a next generation reading
and listening app that's similar to what
Pocket was you know a decade ago but
with a lot of more advanced features and
they started with a focus on reading but
recently they launched a feature called
readable podcasts that allows you to
convert a podcast into a text
transcription. It did other things like
you could double tap your AirPods to
pause and create a highlight out of the
audio transcription. And so it's this
really innovative feature that sort of
expanded the value prop of Matter to a
segment of its users. And that alone
ended up almost doubling subscriber
conversion for the business. And so it's
a great example of even if you already
have product market fit you should
always be on the lookout for those
clusters of users that want more.
There's two parts of it right? There's
market and the product and both of those
are this nebulous problem space. People
have like distributions of needs and use
cases but there's adjacencies and things
and you're moving two sorts of
equilibrium. You're finding folks that
are adjacent to what you know how to do
but have like you're saying some
adjacent need and then you can take your
product and you can also serve them. And
that's actually why companies can scale
cuz that's more efficient than finding
that very first breaking into a market.
Also you're running up against like no
brand no mechanisms of business. You
have nothing. You're starting very
scratch. Yeah like I was saying it's
like why we have such power law outcomes
often in business is because you just
can draft off of these things like
repeatedly. But it still does play into
that robustness argument and the fact
that it's never product market fit even
though it is binary. It's binary for
your first one. Yep. Everything else you
know it's like a repeated process of
Yeah it's incremental.
expansion and yeah exactly. Robust rapid
repeatable remarkable. Let's move on to
rapid. What do you mean by rapid in the
context of value creation? Yeah I think
this one may be the most obvious which
is there more apps than ever out there.
It's really hard to get someone's
attention and it's really easy to lose
it very quickly. I think there was a
study done by Microsoft a number of
years ago that showed that the average
human attention span had dropped by like
50% between 2000 and 2015. I'm sure
there were flaws with that study but
directionally people's attention spans
are getting shorter. I think that's
pretty hard to argue with. Yeah and this
day with TikTok it's devolving even more
quickly.
Hopefully we've hit bedrock with the
assumption but I hope so. I hope so.
Neuralink might change everything.
So the idea here is it's not enough
anymore to create a really compelling
product. You need to make sure people
understand why it matters for them
really really quickly. And so the
companies that do this really well they
take a problem space that in general is
somewhat complex because if it wasn't
then somebody probably would have
already solved it and they really
distill it down to like what is the most
important point for me to get across to
new users in their first session ideally
in the first 30 seconds of them using
the app. Reforge has this framework that
talks about sign up and then moving into
the setup moment the aha moment and the
habit moment. So ultimately you want to
build a sustainable habit with users but
you're never going to get there if you
can't tell them why they should be using
your app in their first session. And so
I like to think about this one in terms
of like how do we remove all of the
noise from those first few onboarding
screens as possible. Front load as much
delight and back load as much work so
that we get the user to the aha moment
as quickly as we can. I was just talking
to Ryan Jones the founder of Flighty.
He's in Austin so we went and had uh
coffee
and he was talking through his
onboarding and we were just talking
through like what he could potentially
do. He's like my onboarding sucks. It's
just a single page. Like I know I need
to do more and I was like I don't know
that you do cuz his product really does
a great job of once you get into the
product he has a lot of little set up
your first flight or like if you don't
have a flight like do a sample flight.
And so that one page of onboarding for
Flighty because the product itself gets
people to that aha moment might not need
this massive onboarding to actually get
to that moment. But then there's so many
apps where maybe you do need that. Are
there some examples you wanted to share
around this getting to that aha moment?
I think that's really well said. I mean
less is more in general when it comes to
onboarding. And so if you can get away
with one or two screens great by all
means do it. But that's not always
practical and so I think one canonical
example of a product that's been really
successful with a longer onboarding flow
is Noom the weight loss and fitness app.
And one of their big insights was that
by asking users more questions they were
actually building more and more intent
because users felt like okay I have an
acute problem that I want solved. I'm
here for a reason and I need your help.
And the more you ask me questions the
more I feel listened to and the more I
feel like this product is actually going
to succeed where many other products
I've tried in the past have failed. And
so there are just like with all of these
and with any framework right? There's
always going to be exceptions. But I
would start from the point of what's the
minimum viable onboarding experience?
Like how quickly can we explain to a
user why this matters?
So a couple other examples I'll give you
on the other end of the spectrum
Reflectly is an app I really love. I
think Reflectly is largely growing
through paid ads and word of mouth. They
have a fairly simple product. It's a
journaling app. There are lots of
journaling apps out there. And so their
onboarding is very short and very
delightful. It's really really well
designed. It gets to the point quickly
and there's a hard paywall pretty
quickly or at least there was the last
time I looked at the app. That's an
example of like all the way on the other
end of the spectrum versus Noom. And in
the middle you have Rise is is another
app that I've been using a lot this year
around sleep and energy management. To
me they're one of the best examples of
onboarding I've seen in recent memory
because they take this really complex
problem around sleep right? Like
everybody sleeps differently. You've got
genetics you've got environmental
factors and it's a really cool challenge
they're solving. It's not a simple one
but you've got to be able to explain to
the user in a minute or less right? Why
this is going to work for them.
And so in a few screens they basically
say imagine there was a drug out there
that could solve all of these problems
for you make you happier healthier more
energetic. That drug is sleep. Now based
on the scientific evidence there's
really only one variable that matters
most and that's sleep debt. And then
they say answer a few questions and we
will help calculate your sleep debt
score and immediately tell you changes
you can make to improve your energy
levels. And so within two minutes you
understand the value prop you understand
the metric that matters most which is
sleep debt. You've provided them with
the minimum amount of information they
need to provide you with the best
possible experience. And then there's an
optional flow where you can connect your
wearable device which many people using
Rise are likely going to be doing. And
then you get this magic output of like
here's your sleep debt based on the last
30 60 90 days of your sleep and here's
what that means in terms of when you
should be going to bed when you should
be waking up when you should stop
drinking caffeine in the morning. And
that's just such a powerful experience.
It takes this really complex problem and
it simplifies it and helps the user
believe that this is going to help them.
I don't know if we talked about this on
that podcast or not but I have since
used that as an example that the
onboarding of Rise is a great example
that the value prop of Rise is sleep
coaching and the onboarding is
delivering that coaching value. Like
what's a good coach? They're going to
ask you some questions. They're going to
inform you of things you didn't know.
They're going to and it's like the
onboarding is actually demonstrating the
value of Rise as a coach. And maybe Noom
is a similar thing of like a good weight
loss plan is not going to be the same
for every person and by asking those
questions it's like demonstrating that
they're going to be a good coach cuz
they're going to take all these
different factors into account when
they're building this custom plan for
you. So it's interesting how onboarding
can actually demonstrate the product
value through asking questions and like
delivering some of that value along the
way versus like leading up to the value
or trying to tell people about the value
but actually helping them experience the
value in the onboarding I think is part
of the key of why that ends up working
as well as it does. It's sales right?
Yeah. This is a sales pitch. This is the
you got two minutes to sell somebody a
time share or whatever it is right? It's
just that you're doing it in the form of
an app. So you have multimedia and
experience and stuff like this. And
maybe that's where some developers
struggle is that maybe they're like
trying to oh it's got to fit in the
interface. It doesn't have to be
whatever. There are no rules. I think
you just highlighted Phil with these
three wildly different examples of
onboarding, right? There's really no
rules. It's like, what is the best way
to make the most compelling human pitch
for what value you're providing? And I
would say it's different cuz it's
consumer, but honestly B2B, like every
sales pitch, you got to hook somebody in
the first 30 seconds, right? Or they're
just like, "Ah, it's not for me." You
think about it, somebody saw something
they attracted, they went through the
beginning of the funnel, they downloaded
your app, and here they are. Like, don't
blow it. You've come a long way to get
them here. If you're an early-stage
person like thinking about, how do I
think about onboarding? I think you can
evaluate product market fit before you
have a good onboarding, right? Like, if
your onboarding can be kind of crappy,
and in fact, I think that can help
reduce the like noise, because if you
have a really good onboarding but a
crappy product, it might like It's a
bridge to nowhere.
Yeah, exactly. If you're asking these
surveys and stuff, people might give you
like weird answers like, "Oh, it's
really beautiful cuz you did a really
good onboarding, but the app sucks, but
I'm going to tell you the onboarding was
good." But if the onboarding's
absolutely garbage, and like people are
still saying, "I love this app," then
you really know
you cracked it. Then yeah, the
onboarding to that, and then it's just
pure rocket fuel, right? Yeah, no, I
think that's exactly right. They
definitely go in that order. And
onboarding's becoming more important
than ever, because even if you do have a
really good product, your early adopters
will stay with you no matter what. And
you guys have made the point that it's
actually a positive signal in some ways
is when you have a really crappy product
and people still want to use it. But
eventually, you'll move past those early
adopters, and especially if you start
relying on paid advertising, then you
better be able to tell someone quickly
why this matters for them. And one last
point before we move on, David, you
brought up this idea of helping the user
to understand why the product is
valuable as they're going through the
onboarding flow. So, Quizlet, we
actually call this immersive onboarding.
The idea was, how can we steep the user
in the product as they are going through
the setup and aha moments. Not every
product can do that. It depends a little
bit on the nature of your product and
your target customer. But there are
plenty of good examples out there of
apps who do. And Rise is one example. I
think Duolingo is another great example,
right? The onboarding is you do a round
of language learning. You answer a few
questions on what language you're
studying, on what your proficiency level
is, and then you're dropped immediately
into this gamified learning experience.
And by the end of it, if you were ever
going to sign up for Duolingo, now's the
time because you're really excited about
what it can do for you. One piece of
context I think a lot of people leave
out in thinking through onboarding is
like, what the experience was before
getting to onboarding. So, if you're
just repeating your top three
screenshots from the App Store, like
people probably have seen that. What ad
did they see? What value prop were you
selling that brought them into the app?
And like, how much awareness do they
already have of that? And then the
onboarding shouldn't just be a repeat of
the first three screenshots in the App
Store, because they've already seen
those. And that's where that term, the
immersive What do you call it? Immersive
onboarding?
Immersive onboarding.
Yeah, that's really cool. Just thinking
through like, you actually at that
point, they downloaded it because they
had a sense that it was going to be
valuable. If it's flighty, if it's a
flight tracking app, it's going to track
flights. You don't need to tell them in
five screenshots that you're going to
track the flights. If they're
downloading Duolingo, you don't need to
tell them in six pages that you're going
to teach them how to learn a language.
It's like, that's the value they're
expecting to get. You want to
demonstrate how you're going to do that
and demonstrate how you're actually
going to deliver that value for them.
And immersive onboarding, that's a great
way to think about helping people get to
that value as quickly as possible. Yeah,
it's the whole idea of show, don't tell,
because you've already told in the App
Store and in your advertising. And so,
once they get to the app, you should be
showing them, not telling them. That's a
great way to think about it. Okay, so,
robust, rapid, repeatable, remarkable.
What is repeatable in the context of
value creation? Repeatable is one of
those that, while the overall framework
might be universal, I think this one is
especially important for subscription
products, right? Because
there are plenty of apps out there, I'm
sure both of you have used some of them,
where the first month you're like, "Man,
this is incredible. How did I never know
about this before?" And then you get
like 60 or 90 days in and you're like,
"Eh,
I've kind of gotten the value I wanted
out of this, and I'm not sure I need it
anymore." And actually, I think early
generations of fitness trackers, Fitbit
being one example, ran into this
challenge a lot. In some ways, it was
why they were a hardware model, right?
Cuz they're getting paid up front.
Obviously, they have to cover their
hardware costs, but another problem was
if all you're really doing is telling
somebody how many steps they walked
every day, and then a few cool analytics
around that, there's sort of a decay
curve to the marginal value that a user
is getting from that experience. And so,
you need to make sure that the value
promise that sits at the center of your
subscription value loop is repeatable,
and that there's sort of like a new
chapter every so often that's going to
bring the user back in. And this also
gets into different types of
subscription products, right? So, with
content products, you just need more
content. Like with Netflix, with
Spotify, with even meditation apps like
Headspace and Calm, a lot of it is a
just new content that will bring people
back. In other cases, like for tools
products, Oura is a good example of
this. Whoop is a good example of this.
It's, how can we build more
functionality? And how can, as a user is
using us for a longer and longer
duration of time, as they're using the
product and looking at it more
frequently, how can we uncover new
insights? I think Oura is a great
example of a product that's done a
really nice job of that. Because if you
don't do that, eventually your
subscribers are going to churn. And
ultimately, consumer subscription
businesses only really work if they have
really high long-term retention rates,
cuz that's what builds the compounding
layer cake of net revenue retention.
Yeah, I think about this a lot with I
mean, things like a document scanner.
Where that really works as a
subscription app is the people who are
regularly scanning documents. But if
you're like, "Oh, I just need to quickly
scan something cuz I'm buying a house,"
and you do that once a decade or
whatever, that's not a repeatable
experience. And so, that's not the core
market for a scanner app. I do feel like
there's a lot of subscription apps out
there now that offer a very, especially
for a broader market, do offer kind of a
more time
encapsulated value prop. It's like, "I'm
going to do things once or twice, and
I'm going to get the value out of it."
And it You don't build a great
subscription app on that. Now, a
document scanner is a good example that
there are a ton of people. I use uh
scanner
to say, David, it's just a product
market thing. Like, you're just in the
You're in the market for which it is not
a great subscription business, but there
may be a market for which it is a good I
I think about this as
need to figure that out, right? Yeah,
cuz like, I was going to say, I use this
app Scanner Pro by Readdle, and I use it
multiple times a month. And I actually
bought it as a paid app years ago, so
I'm not even paying a subscription for
it. But that's an example where I am
part of their target market as a
subscription app, because I am going to
keep scanning multiple documents a month
indefinitely. But then, for other people
who do it once, that's just not the
market that's going to work for that
app. So, yeah, you got to figure out
like, is there a core demographic who is
going to get repeatable value out of it?
Or is this more kind of a one-off value
prop? And if it's a one-off value prop,
it's going to be really hard to build a
good business around that. Yeah, if
that's your product, you better either
be monetizing heavily up front, either
with a lifetime or annual plan. But even
then, you're kind of like building a
castle on sand, right? Because the value
you're delivering is incommensurate with
what you're charging. There's just high
turnover. Those aren't super durable
businesses, right? With the a handful of
exceptions. There was this era, I think
this was pre-ATT and the unit economic
changes on acquisition on the App Store,
but there were just so many of these
like shovelware subscription apps. They
were just trying to extract as much
money before they got caught by the user
kind of situation. And high turnover,
let's put it that way. Like, they did
not survive the ATT apocalypse. They
were subscription businesses in name
only, in the sense, right? That they
were Yeah, they technically set up a
recurring thing, but in terms of having
any sort of durable, repeatable value
delivery and capture, like it wasn't
really there. And time eventually shook
those out. Well, and you mentioned, so
the second exception I was going to make
is
if you can manage to find an organic
acquisition model that is so strong that
you're spending very little money to
acquire users, then maybe maybe it still
works. But those are hard to come by.
If you don't have a repeatable value
prop that can sustain long-term
retention, and your primary growth loop
is paid ads,
that's where you see a graveyard of
companies that have just completely
failed. Yeah, cuz you eventually run
out. Your CAC goes up as you expend your
users. And actually, I think that is
kind of the just to jump to the next R,
this is remarkable, and like efficiency
and virality, right? It's part of that
capture. So, what do you mean by
remarkable? Sorry, David, I stole your
job.
It's fine.
Yeah, so, remarkable is the idea that
there are standout companies like
Tinder, Strava, that have built these
explosive experiences, right? And with
Tinder, it was the swipe mechanic, among
other things. With Strava, it was this
highly engaged community of athletes. If
it didn't happen on Strava, it didn't
happen. But those are the exceptions.
Even if you're not a product that
depends primarily on virality in order
to grow your user base,
ideally, you want a product that is
unique and compelling enough that people
want to talk about it. And you may not
have a K-factor over one, but people are
going to tell their friends and family
members about it. And that does two
things that are important. One, it helps
drive more organic acquisition, which
brings down blended CAC and gives you a
more sustainable business model. But the
other thing it does is it creates this
installed community of users who are
really loyal and talking to each other.
And again, Strava's like a standout
example of this. But when you have that,
it also really helps with long-term
retention. And that's equally if not
more important at the end of the day
than, you know, having a viral product
that has a K-factor over than one, cuz
that's really, really hard to come by. I
think this is something people assume,
"Oh, if I just build a great product,
people will talk about it or whatever."
And to a certain extent, that's true.
But the remarkable part is really
interesting. And again, just being fresh
on my mind having talked to Ryan
recently, the most remarkable part about
Flighty and the stories that get told is
when Flighty tells people 6 hours ahead
of time that their flight's going to be
delayed or 2 hours ahead of time, and
they can actually see that the plane
that's supposed to take them wherever
they're going is not even landed at the
airport or whatever, and they get to
spend 3 more hours at home with their
family instead of sitting at the airport
for 3 hours. Like that's what people
remark when they talk about Flighty.
It's like, "Yeah, it's a great flight
tracker, and yes, it has all these other
great features." It's probably a good
exercise for founders and growth teams
to think like, what is remarkable about
our product? And in that word, it's
like, what will people actually say?
What are people actually saying about
our product when they share? Is there
something that people care enough about
that they're actually going to talk
about it? And can we make it easy?
Right. Yeah. Does something facilitate
that? Yeah, well, and two other things
that I think a lot of companies don't
think about when it comes to having a
remarkable product that drives word of
mouth. So, one is there are different
types of word of mouth loops. There's
the like Facebook example of it just
went viral like wildfire at Harvard and
then everywhere else.
But that's not the only type of
virality. So, you have a personal viral
loop, which is people are inviting
people to the product because it makes
the product more valuable for them. You
have a social viral loop, which is where
people are telling other people about
the product because they want to be one
of the cool kids who knew about it early
on and sort of spread the word. You've
got a financial viral loop, which is
you're actually getting a monetary or
non-monetary reward for inviting other
people. And so, there's subscription
apps like MasterClass, for example, has
done a really good job with that type of
growth strategy. And then there are
casual contact viral loops where
people at a party see someone swiping on
Tinder, and they're like, "Oh, that's
interesting. Maybe I should download
Tinder." Or people are at a marathon,
and they see people recording their run
on Strava, and they think, "Oh, maybe I
should record my run on Strava." So, you
have to think about what your product is
naturally suited for when it comes to
how it's going to drive word of mouth,
and how you design it to match that
flavor of word of mouth. And then, I
think the other thing that people miss
is the fact that so much
word of mouth happens offline, and you
can't measure it easily. And so, there
are exceptions where you can just track
directly in the app like somebody sent a
referral code, or they shared an invite
through this channel, and there's a
unique parameter, and so we know how
many people invited, how many friends
they invited, and how many of those
friends converted. But most of the
activity's happening offline. And so,
there's a tool called the word of mouth
coefficient that allows you to quantify
offline word of mouth by looking at how
many new users are you getting through
channels like direct, branded search, or
social in any given period. So, look at
it over the course of a week, a month,
over your returning users plus any new
users getting through non-organic
channels. And that coefficient is
telling you how efficiently you're
getting new users through word of mouth
from your existing user base. And so,
that's nice because it goes beyond tools
like NPS that aren't really telling you
anything actionable about what you can
do to a tool that quantifies it in more
detail. The word of mouth coefficient I
found I Googled it cuz I need to Google
things, but there's an article on
Reforge about this. Like it's a really
interesting concept of using basically
subtracting out all of your knowns, and
then it's like assuming that that's the
remainder is your word of mouth. Is that
like the basic concept? Yeah, that's the
idea. You're basically backing into what
can we directionally estimate we're
getting in terms of word of mouth new
user acquisition through returning users
and new users who aren't coming in
through organic channels. So, that could
be paid ads, it could be non-branded
search traffic. And the reason it's
powerful is it helps you understand one
like overall similar to K factor,
roughly how many new word of mouth users
are we getting for an existing active
user.
The second reason it's important is
because depending on the nature of your
product, you can actually see word of
mouth coefficient fluctuate quite a bit
for various reasons. And so, I spent
time at Quizlet looking at this, but
I've also worked with several edtech
companies as part of my advising
business. And one of the things you
often see in edtech is your word of
mouth coefficient goes way down over the
summer and during holidays, which makes
sense because nobody's in school. Then
there are these critical back-to-school
periods around August, September in
North America, as well as after the
holidays, where your word of mouth
coefficient spikes way up. And then
there are also a few periods in the
middle of the school year around exams,
where you have these windows of
opportunity to really take advantage of
a much higher word of mouth coefficient.
And then the last piece that was even
more interesting was during the
pandemic, you saw word of mouth
coefficient fall off a cliff when the
pandemic first hit for a lot of edtech
companies. But then what happened after
that really varied by country. And so,
you had countries that kicked into gear
with remote learning really quickly, and
in those countries word of mouth
coefficients actually ended up higher
than they were before the pandemic in
some cases.
And then you had other countries that
took much longer to recover, and you
could see all this in the word of mouth
data. And so, it's a pretty actionable
metric in terms of identifying when you
have these pockets of opportunity to
capture more virality. And then when you
pair that with the type of virality that
your product drives, you can think more
tactically around, "Okay, what does that
mean in terms of what do we do in the
product?" Well, I think that's a great
place to wrap up the four Rs of value
creation, robust, rapid, repeatable, and
remarkable.
The alliteration is amusing. I love your
consultant background and alliterating
these. But it is actually helpful. Like
I'm going to remember that, robust,
rapid, repeatable, remarkable. That's
the idea. If somebody doesn't remember
it, then it never happened.
All right, so let's move on to value
delivery. What do you mean by value
delivery in the context of this
subscription value loop? Yeah, so value
delivery is the idea of, okay, you have
a product that people care about and
want to use. How do you, as
cost-efficiently as possible, get it
into the hands of as many users as
possible and connect them to that value?
And the reason this is so important for
consumer subscription apps, especially
now, is because the playbook for much of
the last decade has been find a product
that people are interested in, and then
go spend a bunch of money on Google and
Meta to acquire users and make sure LTV
CAC is high enough for the business to
work, and keep your fingers crossed that
that will last. I'm oversimplifying it.
But that playbook no longer works for a
variety of reasons. One, the app stores
have just gotten much more crowded, so
there's a lot more competition. Two,
there's all of the challenges presented
by ATT and iOS 14, where paid marketing
is a lot less efficient than it used to
be. And then the third, which is not the
most important, but it's a factor, is
venture capital funding is harder to
come by now. And so, if your plan was,
"Well, we're going to scale until we hit
a tipping point where the economics
work, and we can do that because we're
going to go raise a large seed and
series A round." That doesn't work
anymore, at least not in this market
environment.
Certainly not in consumer, right?
Yeah. And not when interest rates are
non-zero.
That capital needs a faster return on
investment and a more sure return on
investment. Yeah, so I was going to say,
I'm not going to go into as much detail
on value delivery as I do on value
creation value capture. But the number
one point I want to make on value
delivery is that the best consumer
subscription companies, almost without
exception, and the ones that have really
stood the test of time, have really
robust organic acquisition strategies
that are their primary growth lever. And
they only use paid ads as a supplement.
What are some examples of that? So, I
think you can divide them into two
categories. You've got companies that
have really been able to grow through
word of mouth. The other big one is
content. So, there are a few different
flavors of this. Quizlet's an example of
a company that has done a really nice
job growing through long-tail SEO,
right? There's so much flashcards
content created on Quizlet by students,
by teachers. And so, even though there
are plenty of other edtech companies out
there competing for head terms, Quizlet
has a really strong advantage in
long-tail search queries. So, that's one
good example of a company that has been
able to find this kind of unique way of
scaling without having to spend a lot of
money. Another good example is
AllTrails, which I know has been on the
podcast. And for them, long-tail search
I'm sure was relevant as well, but
hyper-local search I'm sure was a big
advantage for them because if I'm
looking for where I want to go on a hike
or a trail run, I'm probably, by and
large, looking within 5, 10 miles of my
home. And so, you know, as is the case
with all of these things, you sort of
got to double-click and triple-click
before you get to the real insights. But
I think companies that can generate
user-generated content that's organic to
the product experience, and ideally pair
that user-generated content with a
unique and differentiated SEO strategy,
can really be successful in the long
run. Yeah, and there's probably like 10
other ways that that works. You could
probably do a whole podcast on all the
different kind of organic loops that
work for different apps for different
reasons, for different contexts, for
different markets, for different
whatever. But yeah, I think that's a
good summary. We do talk a ton on the
podcast about value delivery, and about
getting attention for your app, about
getting people to the app store, about
marketing and everything else. One point
that still has an interesting we talked
about earlier, there's always this wall
eventually
that LTV and CAC sort of normalize
because you push beyond your product
market fit, you've pushed into like a
less spendy market. Like eventually it
loses steam. It might be at scale A,
scale B, scale C, right? You know, some
order of magnitude difference between
those two, but it will die out. All of
the things we talked about before make
that number a little bit further in the
future. Better word of mouth, all these
things, like better product, make that
all a little bit more efficient, but at
the end of the day, you're only going to
be able to scale it so far. And so, I
mean, I think that just supports your
point, and which is a benefit for the
world. Like, I think we've entered an
even better era. I was not super
thrilled with the ZIRP era of apps, as
we mentioned before, and I think we've
entered a better world where, as you
said, talk about value capture, right?
Like, value creation, value capture,
delivery, and all that stuff. Let's let
the App Store handle that. That's where
we've been there.
You know, it's kind of a nice great
thing. Yeah, there's this idea of
painkillers versus vitamins, and I think
ZIRP allowed a lot of vitamins to hang
around. But, at the end of the day, if
your product isn't solving a real need,
then
it's probably not going to last. And so,
I think as ZIRP has subsided, there's
just been a lot of companies left
holding the bag who don't really have an
answer for it. So, the last part of the
subscription value loop is value
capture. And this is one I do want to
deep dive into, and we do talk about
this a lot on the podcast, but it's just
such a fundamental part that's hard. You
know, you create value, but value and
finding the right balance of how much
value you give to the users and how much
value you take, and finding that right
balance is really tricky. So, tell me
about value capture. Yeah, so value
capture is this idea that, to go back to
the car analogy, your subscription
revenue is your fuel. And so, even if
you build a really nice car, if it
doesn't have enough fuel to run, it's
ultimately going to sputter out and
fail.
And so, I think what's interesting about
this step is you can almost think of
different categories of companies in
terms of where they are strong versus
weak in the subscription value loop. And
so, the companies that are really,
really strong at value creation, they
have a great product, they're going to
get past that initial product market fit
phase, they're at least going to get to
the point where they're scaling the
business, but they may run into a wall
if they can't be efficient about one or
both of value delivery and value
capture. On the other end of the
spectrum, you have the companies that
are really good at value capture, but
they're not good at value creation.
Well, they're probably never really
going to get much past the starting
gate, right? And so, what's interesting
about value capture, and a lot of my
advising work centers around this step,
is you really want these companies to
succeed that have done a great job
building a great product, but they just
haven't quite figured out how to get
enough value back out of the system to
keep the car running.
And I even run sometimes into We ran
into this a little bit at Quizlet, where
Quizlet is such a mission-driven
company, and it's done so much good in
the world for teachers and students, but
there were times where I was like, well,
should we be monetizing this product
less than we are? Like, ultimately, this
is an education app, we want to do
everything we can to advance education,
but it doesn't have to be a zero-sum
game. And the more resources that you
can invest back into your product, the
better you're going to be able to
deliver value to customers, the longer
your business is going to last, and the
more flexible you can be in terms of
deciding, okay, maybe we have tiered
subscription plans, or maybe we have a
freemium model, and that way we can
subsidize users that don't have the
resources to pay for the product while
still having a sustainable business. And
so, value capture is all about making
sure the car keeps running. You want to
leave surplus, right? Is that what
you're saying? It's it's a debate on how
much to capture. You can capture none,
you'll go out of business. But, at the
end of the day, you should be allowed to
capture enough that you're still
delivering a net value, you know, if you
put dollars on it, you create $100 of
value for your customer, you charge them
50, like, they're still ahead. Nobody
should be mad about that, right? Like,
people get real icky about monetization,
but like, you know, with the energy
analogies, again, I know, but it's the
car analogy, the same thing. It's you've
created a little engine, and extracting
the fuel from the engine is why these
things grow. We just Actually, different
than the car analogy, where you bring
the fuel in from somewhere else. It's
actually a perpetual motion machine,
more so. The point you make about And
it's maybe a bit hand-wavy if you're
having that conversation with yourself
about like, you know, are we capturing
too much value? Are we like off of our
mission? But if you like actually are
investing that capture back into the
product, it's not, right? Like, and I
guess that depends on what you do with
the profits of a business. It just goes
into like the fundamentals of
capitalism, right? Are you reinvesting
that in growth? Are you reinvesting that
in product? Are you reinvesting that in
both? You're not only leaving a value
surplus, and depending on how much you
capture, but you're also leveraging that
investment into hopefully even more
value creation for the customer. Lots of
hands getting waved in like the
accounting on that, right? Like, it's
really hard. Well, and I think there are
exogenous forces that dictate, in most
cases, at least with consumer
subscription apps, that a lot of the
value will be reinvested into the
business. For two reasons. One is
because the companies that make it far
enough to where they're really honing
their value capture engine, they have
great To your point earlier, right? You
have probably haven't hired a large
growth team until you've gotten to the
point where you have a really compelling
product and a large user base. So, the
companies that have made it this far
have made it this far for a reason, and
they have a compelling product, and
they're not mercenaries, or they
probably wouldn't have made it this far.
The second, and probably more important
reason, is the competitive forces around
consumer subscription, unless you have a
really, really strong network effect,
which most consumer subscription apps
don't, you can't afford not to reinvest
a lot of that value into the product.
Because if you don't, somebody will come
along, and they will, and eventually,
they'll leapfrog you. You talked about a
freemium strategy as the paid users
subsidizing the value that you're giving
away for free to the free users,
but you can and do actually capture some
amount of value from the free users. And
if you're using a freemium model, you
should be thinking about what value
you're capturing from those free users.
And a good example is AllTrails, which
we've talked about a lot, but part of
the reason their freemium strategy works
is that those free users are helping
update the data and adding new trails,
and it's like they're actually
contributing value back into the loop.
And AllTrails has I think they have some
minimal ads and some sponsorships and
things like that, and they have merch,
and they have other things. And so, when
thinking about value capture, we're
mostly going to talk about value capture
in relation to capture through
subscription. But when you have a
freemium model, you should still also be
thinking about what value those free
users are adding to the equation. So,
before we move on to the subscription
value capture, what are your thoughts on
that value capture from the free users?
I think that's spot-on, and as with so
many things, you need to tailor
your strategy around the fundamental
constraints of your business. So, in
this case, your growth loops that drive
your business will dictate things like,
what is our trial strategy? How
aggressive or conservative are we going
to be with our paywall placement? And
for a product like AllTrails or Quizlet,
for that matter, where so much of the
growth is being driven organically,
you're getting a ton of value out of
those free users. In fact, I would argue
you're getting value that the business
would struggle to exist without, or at
least it would be much less valuable,
right? Because they are the engine that
is driving compounding growth. On the
other end of that spectrum, though,
there are cases where you have a product
that free users might hang around and
dabble, and they might write into
customer support every once in a while,
and they're not adding zero value, but
the amount of value they're adding is so
incommensurate with the amount of time
and maintenance and energy that a
company can be spending to support them,
that it's not always the case that you
want to cater to that free user segment.
It just really depends on your product
and your business model. And into your
point with Quizlet, I mean, it's
perfectly acceptable as a business to
say part of our mission as a company is
to deliver excess value, and part of how
we're going to do that is to give way
more away to these free users and let
the paid users subsidize it. But, you
need to think about is that what we're
doing, or do we need to capture more
value from the free users, or how do we
capture more value from the free users?
So, I think it's kind of an interesting
thought exercise on the freemium side of
the equation. I think that's right, and
I think part of the reason that Quizlet
is now one of the most valuable edtech
companies in the world is because
they've given away so much value for so
long. In their case, it really does make
sense for their model. It's built this
really compelling community,
not just among students, but there's
this cross-side network effect between
teachers and students that creates this
really virtuous cycle, improves
retention, improves viral word of mouth.
And it's because Quizlet had no
subscription for the first many years of
its existence, didn't even have ads for
a long time, and even after it
introduced a subscription, kept its
prices quite low, that allowed the
company to build this really strong moat
and its brand around we're going to do
good, we're going to put our students
and teachers first. And there are a lot
of companies that tried to sort of take
the shortcut and monetize more rapidly
that ultimately ended up failing because
Quizlet just had such an advantage when
it came to acquisition. So, let's move
on to the five P's of value capture.
Paywall, pricing and packaging,
payments, and promotions. So, it's four
categories, five P's.
I bundled pricing and packaging
together. It makes sense. It makes Such
a classic pair.
So, let's talk about paywall. In the
context of the value capture, how should
you be thinking about paywalls? I'll
sort of break this one into two parts.
There's standard stuff that you can and
should do with your paywall that kind of
applies to just about any consumer or
prosumer subscription app. And I know
you've had Jake Moore from Superwall on
the podcast a couple of times. I think
he's talked through a lot of these. So,
things like, when you're first getting
started, err on the side of being
aggressive with your paywall, because
one, it will help you start to make
revenue, but two, it will really filter
out the users who are your early
adopters, who value your premium product
the most. So, that makes a lot of sense.
And then, there's tactics around use
visuals, a picture's worth a thousand
words, a video's better than an image,
like, make your paywall as compelling as
possible, keep your feature list short,
lead with an emotional appeal. A lot of
this just goes back to front-load
delight, make things as easy as possible
for the user. Like, a lot of users don't
even read all the text on the paywall,
right? And so, it's got to be quick and
easy to consume. I think where things
get really interesting is when you start
to move one layer deeper than the sort
of general best practices around paywall
and get into the specifics around what
makes sense for your business depending
on factors like the nature of your
product. So, if you have a simpler
product, you probably can afford to be
more aggressive with your paywall. If
you have more complex product, you're
likely going to need to give the user a
little bit more time to experience it
before you ask them to put their credit
card down. Pricing, similar. Like if you
have a really high price, you're going
to need to be more conservative. If you
have a lower price, you can probably be
more aggressive. Growth loops we already
covered. So, if user-generated content
or viral word of mouth are core to your
growth strategy,
probably want to have a freemium app
experience and create a great experience
for free users. But if you're a
paid-to-play subscription where it's all
about just funneling revenue back into
paid ads, then you can be more
aggressive. And then there are a few
other factors like so target users,
adults and prosumers are probably going
to be a little bit more patient and have
a little bit more money to spend versus
students or teenagers. So, you have to
keep that in mind. Competition is an
obvious one. So, like the more viable
substitutes there are for your product,
the more you're probably going to need
to be generous with your paywall. And
then the last one is trial strategy. So,
where you place the paywall, how
aggressively you place the paywall,
needs to be compatible with how you've
structured your free trial. If you're
giving away a month free, then paywall
away because it's a very soft paywall,
right? People are still going to get a
lot of time to experience the core value
prop. But if it's a 3-day free trial or
if there's no trial at all, then you
probably want to be a little bit more
thoughtful about where you put that
experience. What are some good examples
that you've seen of effective paywall
strategies? I'll give a couple of
outside-in examples that I've just
observed companies doing what I would
consider to be a really good job with
this. And then I have one example of a
company that I'm working with directly
now, that I mentioned before, Matter,
that actually saw pretty significant
improvements from some of these changes.
To start with, Calm I think is a company
that gets referenced a lot in terms of
their paywall design. There's the
obvious stuff. They lead with an
emotional appeal. They have this nice
calming imagery of people resting,
meditating. Their feature list is short
and pithy. It doesn't take a lot of time
to read or digest. They use the standard
Amazon yellow best deal recommended tags
to highlight the annual plan. They break
down the like effective monthly rate of
the annual plan versus the monthly plan.
They're all the like blocking and
tackling stuff that they do really well.
I think the more subtle thing that is
easy to miss with Calm's paywall is
one, it's very much built for mobile
because most of Calm's consumers are
purchasing on mobile and using the app
on mobile as opposed to desktop. They do
have a desktop paywall, but it's I would
guess it's not what most people are
going to.
And then the second piece is the secret
to Calm's success in leapfrogging
Headspace in many ways was stumbling
across this idea of sleep stories and
really solving the most acute pain point
people have in this mindfulness space,
which is sleeping better.
And so, if you look at their paywall,
imagine it's midnight or 1:00 in the
morning and you can't sleep. You've got
racing thoughts. You open your Calm app.
Maybe you heard about it from a friend
or you've been considering paying for
it. And it's like this nice soft blue
palette. It uses a lot of calming
language. It's just very tailored for
their customer and the mind space that
their customer is going to be in when
they're getting to that purchase
decision.
And so, I think that's an example of
going beyond the generic advice, going
beyond the frameworks and actually
applying judgment around what's going to
work for their consumer. I know that
Calm has also experimented a lot now and
is leaning in toward customizing the
paywall experience for different entry
points.
So, like if you enter I was playing with
the app recently and I'm not currently a
subscriber. So, when you enter from like
whatever famous person, Matthew
McConaughey reads me to sleep. I think
they have like sleep stories from him.
It's like you tap on that button and
then it follows through with Matthew
McConaughey. But if you hit the paywall
without that context, you're not seeing
celebrities, you're seeing different
sets of value prop. And so, you know,
and it's a big team and they're able to
do this. You know, it's harder as a
small app to figure out every different
entry point and all that. But over time,
figuring out those entry points and even
potentially customizing the paywall to
the entry points can be a very effective
way to do it. And I think Calm is really
killing it on that front. Yeah, I think
that's something where you've seen a lot
more innovation recently is
personalizing the paywall or customizing
it based on the channel the user came in
through or even based on in-app signals
that you've gotten about the user
depending on where the paywall is
placed. Yeah, any other examples top of
mind on great paywall strategies? I
think one other example that a lot of
people point to is Duolingo. I talked
about their immersive onboarding
experience and getting the user to the
point where they're really excited about
the product before they get to the
paywall. Above and beyond all of the
standard advice, I think one thing
Duolingo really differentiates itself on
is this personification of the app
through Duo, their owl mascot. And when
you convert into a trial with Duolingo,
which is now Super Duolingo is what
they're calling it. It used to be
Duolingo Plus, now it's Super Duolingo.
Duo turns into an astronaut. The whole
chrome of the app experience changes,
the color, the look, the feel. There's
more animation. That's a missed
opportunity that I think a lot of
obviously you're not going to do an
optimization like this as a smaller
company. But when you get to the point
where
there's a lot of leverage in optimizing
trial start and trial conversion, doing
something like that that really
celebrates that purchase moment, I think
can be really powerful. And then the
last example I was going to give is this
company that I've been working with,
Matter, that I mentioned previously, the
reading app. So, we followed a lot of
the standard advice that Jake provided
in terms of just making the paywall more
prominent, looking at paywall view rate.
So, like what percentage of all users
who install the app are actually viewing
the paywall at least once in their first
session, in their first week, in their
first month.
And by being a little bit more
aggressive about where we place the
paywall, but then also by optimizing
copy, visuals, and a number of other
things, Matter ended up more than
doubling the paywall view rate. And then
that translated into about a 30%
increase in subscriber conversion. And
so, these things like a lot of them seem
small, but in the aggregate they can
actually lead to some pretty significant
improvements. Yeah, 30% and doubling the
paywall view rate, which we hear that a
lot. We've talked to a lot of folks in
the podcast like people who didn't have
the paywall in onboarding, they move it
to onboarding, which like for them
sometimes it's like a 100x because the
paywall was so deeply buried in the app
experience that they're showing the
paywall way more than double. And then
it's like 5x-ing revenue, not even just
a 30% increase. But if you're already
fairly optimized, there's still
opportunities to increase by 30%, which
is crazy. I remember doing optimization
stuff around Elevate in the back in the
day and like everything is just how
close it is to the starting point.
There's things you can do, you can
shuffle things around, but there's kind
of an exponential decay curve in like
who sees what in an app. And then also
you have your home screen in the app.
That's where 90% of the eyeball minutes
are going to be, 95% of the eyeball
minutes. That's not even a paywall hack,
it's a good strategy, but it's just like
make sure every And this is something I
learned from a Zynga person. Zynga
people are really good at monetization,
but like
the user should always be one click away
from buying. You know, you design a
store the same way. Like you don't go
into a store and there's like massive
parts of the store where you can't buy
things, right? Like the whole purpose of
it is to buy stuff. And you have to
think about your app in the same way if
you're monetizing. You don't have to be
gauche about it. Like you can do it
tastefully, but you should always be
subtly reminding your customers like,
"Hey." And that's why I like the
Duolingo example. I didn't know they
changed the chrome cuz I think that's a
really easy way to remind users you
don't have pro. Just so you know, you're
not paying, right? And even if they
don't get any features, right? It's just
kind of a subtle psychology thing.
We still love you, but you're not quite
as special as you could be. Yeah, I
mean, I think you can make the argument
that a lot of subscription apps in some
degree are luxury product. You don't
need Duolingo to survive. You certainly
don't need Duolingo Pro to survive,
right? You don't need like things. So,
you can take some pages out of what the
automotive industry does and like the
luxury goods industry and think about it
in some ways as a display of status,
right? I guess that's more about what's
behind the paywall, but as you're
leading somebody through that paywall as
well, you're selling them on what life's
going to be like on the other side for
them, you know what I mean? Like, "Oh,
come on. You've got Oh, sir, $8 a month.
Wow, big spender. Come on in, right?
Like Well, and to that point, I've found
this isn't always the right answer, but
in a lot of cases there's this one-two
punch of trigger a paywall in a user's
first session. Whether that's
immediately after sign-up or at the end
of an onboarding flow depends on the
product. But make sure that a user sees
the paywall in their first session
because you'd be shocked how many users
of consumer subscription apps don't even
know there is a premium version of the
product. But then pair that with a set
of more customized paywalls that are
tied to your best premium value props
and meter them. So, you have a free
number of uses, but once you get to the
end of that free usage quota, then you
get a customized paywall that's really
honed around that feature.
And I think what's nice about that is
you solve the paywall view rate problem
that Jake talks about, which is you got
to first just make sure people know your
premium product exists. But then instead
of like tapping them on the shoulder
every single time they open the app,
which gets really annoying really
quickly and it's going to churn out a
lot of your free users. Instead, like
align the ask around purchasing the
product with when the user is actually
experiencing the value. Yeah, and then
being thoughtful about where those like
limitations to free usage are. I think a
lot of data I'm sure you've talked to
plenty of indies. This is like classic
indie mistake is like, "Oh, I'm going to
bury the purchase thing like in the
settings, whatever." And like you
actually have quite a compelling pro
offering. Some cases you're just like
embarrassed to like pull it forward.
This is some advice I had from a mentor,
but just being like, "These people are
getting an app for free. They can look
at an app. They can look at the price
tag. They're not going to die." We used
to be like, "Don't be annoying about it.
Like be thoughtful. You don't want to
degrade your free user experience
completely. But it's okay for free users
to give something up. If that's just a
little bit of degradation in user
experience, that's okay.
If you do it right, the paywall moment
in and of itself could be delightful. I
think Duolingo's a great example of
that. Like even if you decide not to
pay, like, "Oh, Duolingo in an astronaut
suit, that's a trip." I mean, I think
that's a great guiding principle from
like product design and business design
in general. It's like even bad moments
in a business, they're in support, like
something's bad, you know, whatever,
even incident. Like whatever it is,
there's always ways to think about how
you can take that moment and turn it
into a net positive experience. And
sometimes it's just little things,
right? It's like framings and copy and
offering to like make it right.
That applies to monetization as well.
The walls and like where you hit stuff,
so. Yeah. And I think you have a little
more flexibility to your point, Phil,
about churning out free users by
annoying them. It's like the more value
you're creating for those users, the
more leeway you have to demand something
of them. So like MyFitnessPal, I'm not
currently subscribed, but I still check
calories every once in a while, check my
macros or whatever. Every single time
you open the app, they show a paywall.
I'm not as annoyed anymore because it's
like I'm getting so much value when I
use it, it's a fair trade, right? Yep.
I mean, we've talked about it a lot
today that that kind of balance of how
much value you're creating and how much
value you're capturing,
that paywall moment, you just have so
much more leeway with those free users
if you're giving them so much value.
But moving on from paywall, pricing and
packaging are the next two P's of value
capture. Let's talk pricing and
packaging. When you look at each of the
steps in the subscription value loop,
and then you look at the individual
levers within each step, this is one of
those along with onboarding and a couple
others that has the most leverage.
Getting pricing and packaging right, I
think there've been a few episodes you
all have had guests on that have said,
"Well, pricing in the early days doesn't
really matter." And I agree with that.
Like in the early days, just find
product market fit. But once you get to
the world I've spent most of my career
in, series B, series C, trying to get to
the point where you can go public,
pricing really, really matters. And it's
really hard to do well. And so, one of
the things that I try to help clients
with in my advising business is
using some pretty standard tools out
there, like Van Westendorp and conjoint
analysis, to really get to at least a
more accurate view of what the optimal
price is for your product. So to just
briefly break those two down, Van
Westendorp analysis, I actually was
listening to the latest podcast episode
on my run this morning.
And so I know the CEO at Ladder
mentioned Van Westendorp last week, so I
won't go into too much detail. But the
idea is basically, you can't ask a user
directly, "How much would you pay for
this product?" because research has
shown they're going to generally give
you a lower price than is actually what
they'd be willing to pay because they
know that any answer they give you could
impact what you end up charging. So
instead, you ask a range. You ask, "At
what price would this product feel like
it was really expensive? At what price
would it feel like it's starting to
become more of a bargain? At what price
would it feel inexpensive, like a really
good deal? And at what price would it
feel too inexpensive, meaning you'd
actually question the quality of the
product?" And then by doing that, you
can generate what's called the Van
Westendorp, it's basically a price
sensitivity meter. And so it shows you
these intersection points between those
four curves, and it gives you an optimal
price range and also an optimal price
point somewhere within that range.
This tool is really good when you're
just looking at what is the overall
willingness to pay for my product in the
aggregate, or as was mentioned on the
Ladder episode, you can cut it by
segments of users. So if I want to know
for students versus teachers, or for
college students versus high school
students, what willingness to pay looks
like, you can do that segmentation. It's
not as good at pinpointing willingness
to pay for individual features. And so
that's where conjoint analysis can be a
helpful supplementary tool because what
conjoint does is it presents the users
with a set of alternatives. It could be
two packages, it could be three
packages, usually it's no more than two
to four.
And each package has a list of
attributes. So this could be price, it
could be number of super likes per month
in the case of a dating app like Tinder
or Bumble. So it could be a range, or it
could be binary. So it could be a
feature that you either get or you don't
get. And then every user is asked to go
through anywhere from like five to 10 of
these conjoint tasks where they pick
whichever package they like the most.
And by doing enough of these, again,
there's a formula that will sort of spit
out, "Okay, what is the relative
importance of each of these attributes?
What is the marginal willingness to pay
for each level within each attribute?"
So how much more am I willing to pay for
five likes versus 10 super likes versus
20 super likes?
And when you do all that, you can really
hone in on not just how much are people
willing to pay overall, but what are the
premium features that are driving most
of the monetization for a business? And
again, how does that vary by user
segment? Where does price testing fit
into this? Is this kind of like
hypothesis validation? Start with Van
Westendorp and conjoint analysis, and
then start testing whether your
hypothesis formed by this analysis is
actually correct? Yeah, that's right.
And I view them as tools in the same
toolkit. And I've even had a healthy
debate with a couple of my clients
around like, "Why don't we just do an AB
test? Like why do we even need to run a
survey?"
And sometimes that's the right answer.
Like in general, the ultimate survey.
Yeah, exactly. I mean, that's the real
acid test, right? I'll give you an
example. I work with EdTech company down
in South America called U Docks. And
they had two tiers, so they had U Docks
Light and U Docks Pro. And then they had
monthly and annual subscriptions. And
one thing I'll say right up front is
when you're an early stage consumer
company, ideally you want one plan. You
want one plan that is either annual only
or that is monthly and annual because
any more complexity than that and you're
going to lose conversion on the margin
simply because people don't have the
attention span to make a decision that's
that complex. If they're a prosumer or
it's B2B SaaS, different story. But for
consumer, you want to keep it as simple
as possible. So we could have run an AB
test. And if we'd run an AB test, we
would have figured out what is the
optimal annual and monthly price for the
Light and Pro tiers, respectively. But
what happened is we ran the Van
Westendorp and we looked at the Light
versus Pro plans with the Van Westendorp
analysis.
And we saw that the marginal willingness
to pay for the Pro plan was very, very
small relative to the Light plan. And we
also found that the marginal willingness
to pay for annual relative to monthly
was fairly low. And in some cases, this
just comes down to you're talking about
college students in South America, they
don't have a ton of disposable income in
a lot of cases. So some of it just comes
down to the ability to pay for the
product. But then we did the conjoint,
and in the conjoint, we actually found
that student interest in ebook content
generated by publishers, that was like
the big incremental value prop for the
Pro plan was you don't just get access
to user generated content, you get
professional publisher content, was
actually in many cases the lowest
marginal to pay premium feature.
And so as a result, what the company
ended up doing was streamlining down to
a single tier, just getting rid of the
Pro tier and only having what they now
call U Docks Plus, and then lowering
their annual price.
And so they had a much simpler set of
plans. They had a lower annual price
that was more aligned with willingness
to pay of their target user base. And
then also importantly, because they got
rid of the ebook content, which had a
pretty significant cost component to it
because they had licensing deals with
these publishers, they actually improved
their margins and as a result, their LTV
CAC ratio. And so in the aggregate, and
I've talked to the founder about sharing
this information, in the aggregate, this
ended up driving a 12% increase in
subscriber conversion and a 10% increase
in net subscription revenue. So this is
a case where AB testing's fast and it's
effective, but it's kind of a blunt
instrument. And surveys can sort of give
you some deeper insights when you do
them the right way. Yeah. And then doing
the Van Westendorp and the conjoint
analysis helps you create a thesis for
why the prices you're going to test
should be tested versus just throwing
crap against the wall and see what
sticks.
favorite method.
It works. It works until it doesn't.
Hold your finger in the wind, be like,
$4.99.
That's the right answer for the early
days.
Yeah.
So the next P is payments. What do you
mean by payments in this context? Yeah,
so payments I break down into a few
things. One is I think a lot of people
don't realize the degree to which
alternative payment methods or APMs are
surpassing in many cases credit cards,
the biggest ones being obviously Visa,
MasterCard, American Express,
as the primary form of e-commerce,
right? Like that's happening in a lot of
international markets, and it's even
starting to happen in the US. And so one
is just making sure you're aware of the
alternative payment methods that really
matter in your geography and for your
user base.
The second is your purchase flow and
just making sure that you're being as
clear and transparent as possible with
users around how your trial works. And
so the canonical example here is the
Blinkist ethical subscription design
pattern, which I think JC Day was on
your podcast and talked about how
effective that was. Quizlet ended up
adopting that pattern, a lot of other
consumer apps have as well. It's one of
these rare win-wins where it drives a
huge amount of incremental upside in
terms of subscriber conversion revenue,
but it's also just the right thing to
do. Like it it really builds trust with
your users. And then the last one is
cancellation flows. And this is one that
I think is tricky, right? Because you
want to remind the user of what they're
losing if they give up the premium plan.
But you don't want to be a jerk, right?
You don't want to adopt these black hat
patterns that a lot of companies
end up doing, in some cases just because
they see all the other companies doing
it. And so you need to make sure that
your cancellation flow is easy to find.
You need to make sure that you're not
preventing users from canceling the
subscription if that's what they want to
do. But it's okay to remind them along
the way, like, "Hey, why are you
leaving? Can we fix it? Is the price too
high? Okay, we can offer you a discount.
Is it something else? Like is there
anything we can do to ameliorate this?"
And if the answer is no, then fine, they
cancel. And I think this is going to
become more and more important because
there's legislation that is working its
way through at both the federal and
state level now in the US that is
actually going to mandate that more and
more subscription apps basically make it
as easy to cancel as it was to sign up.
And so you're not going to be able to
get away with some of this stuff that
some companies have been doing for a
while where you you sort of make
cancellation really difficult to find.
Yeah, and the app stores make that
really easy.
But I did want to highlight when you
were talking about alternative payment
methods. I've been hearing this from
RevenueCat customers
that when they are offering web
payments, it's not enough to just offer
like credit card and Apple Pay. And
Apple Pay is kind of the happy easy path
for a lot of folks. But like pay with
Venmo, pay with PayPal, all those It's
like if somebody's potentially going to
give you money, make it as easy as
possible for them to give you that
money. And some of those alternative
payment methods, even in the US,
actually can drive incremental revenue
just by making it that much easier for
people to pay outside of the app store.
Well, I mentioned so there's the US,
which is the primary market for a lot of
consumer subscription apps. But this is
even more important in a lot of
international markets. And when we
looked at this at Quizlet, we didn't do
a ton of this while I was at the
company, but we started to look at it
because we wanted to make sure that we
weren't just bringing in more users in
international markets, we were actually
monetizing as many of them as we could.
It's a shockingly high percentage of
users in certain country. Like Germany's
a great example. You've got SEPA in
other markets like in the Netherlands,
it's iDEAL. You've got Sofort. In South
America, there's Boleto. In Brazil,
there's Oxxo in Mexico. So you kind of
got to know, if you're a US company
expanding into some of these countries
or if you're an international company,
just make sure you know what the numbers
are in terms of how many of your
potential subscribers are going to pay
with these. Feature request, Jacob.
RevenueCat needs to make this easy for
developers. We need to accept like
thousands of different payment I can
neither confirm nor deny anything about
our road map, so.
All right, the last P for us to touch on
today as we wrap up is promotions. And I
do think this is a really important one.
So I'm curious to hear exactly how you
think about the usefulness of promotions
in this value capture step. Well, this
one feels timely because we've all just
been through Black Friday and Cyber
Monday. And so I'm sure like me, you've
just been inundated with deal after deal
after deal and act now and don't miss
out, best deal of the year. And I think
this gets at the key point I want to
make with promotions. Because, you know,
promotions are not rocket science,
right? It's a tool just like a lot of
these things are. It's a tool to
better align the value of your product
with the willingness to pay of an
individual customer.
And by doing so to capture more consumer
surplus for your business. The key
though is you got to be targeted and
thoughtful about it. And so I actually
think we've seen a little bit an over
rotation on the amount of act now Black
Friday deals. I mean, that certainly has
its place.
I actually think the companies that are
doing this best are for holiday deals
and other sort of seasonal promotions,
they're really injecting their own
personality and brand into it so that it
stands out. And then there are these
more sophisticated techniques. So one of
them is activity-based discounts. So if
a user comes in and they don't subscribe
within the first 24 hours, look at the
point where 90% of your subscribers
typically convert. And then whatever
that time period is, at that point if a
user hasn't converted, offer them a
discount. I think that's a really
effective method because the user is
giving you a direct signal on their
level of intent willingness to pay based
off of their activity in in the app. So
that's a good one. And then I think the
last one is geography-based. Or there
are many cases where you can't segment
based on demographic, but where you can
use demographic or psychographic
information to just better align the
price of your product with the customer.
I think that's where most of the value
is. I've been talking a lot about
tiering as a way to expand the number of
points along that price value curve. But
in prepping for this podcast and talking
to you, it kind of dawns on me that
promotions are another very effective
way to do that. Is that If you would
potentially consider doing a premium
tier, that's a lot of bandwidth on
separating out the features and a lot of
cognitive load like you said with the
YouDocs example of having multiple
tiers. So the first step before you go
to tiering your subscription is start
experimenting with promotions. See if
you can meet more people on that value
demand curve by offering them discounts.
And yeah, I mean, more and more apps are
using it. It's not like this is rocket
science or some like amazing revelation,
but it is something that I think is a
great way to meet more customers where
they're at. It's it's labor-intensive,
too. I think is one of these things that
why it's a tactic you layer in a little
bit later. When you're spending more of
your time on value capture, you have
extra lanes for like a growth team or
somebody to focus on this.
It was a huge unlock almost 10 years ago
now, I guess. But like at Elevate, huge
unlock for us to run stuff. And I think
we also just have the cover in our
society that like people don't get that
mad when things go on sale. Like it's an
expectation that if I buy in normal time
or I will wait. This year there's kind
of an interesting backlash on Black
Friday specifically, I feel like. Maybe
you're right, Phil. Like maybe this is
over. Maybe we're on the way out. But we
make a product with essentially zero
marginal cost, right? It would be very
silly for us to only sell at one price
point. So finding good ways to do that,
to like unlock more of that demand that
you're just leaving on the table, is
smart, right? I think that's right. And
I also think sometimes people look at
price discrimination, even the word
price discrimination sounds negative.
a rebranding there. That's why I say
capturing consumer surplus. But in all
seriousness, you have to look at it both
ways. Like one way to look at it is,
well, they're discounting so that they
can bring more users into the product
that otherwise wouldn't pay. And isn't
that unfair to the users who are willing
to pay a higher price? But the other way
to look at it is if a company isn't able
to monetize those lower willingness to
pay users or the users that simply don't
have the resources to be able to pay but
really want the product, then they are
actually forced in many cases to set
their price higher to make the economics
work, which ends up hurting everyone.
And so there is an argument to be made
that done thoughtfully, this is actually
better. It's certainly better for the
business. And it can go way too far. But
done thoughtfully, it can actually
benefit the consumer as well. Well, I
think that's a great place to wrap up.
Phil, it was really fun talking to you.
And I don't feel like we could have done
this justice. I specifically decided to
make this the first long podcast because
it was just so much to go through in
this loop, this framework that you
developed. But as we wrap up, anything
else you wanted to share? Well, first of
all, I just wanted to thank you all. As
you know, David, and as you found out
earlier, Jacob, I've been a fan of your
podcast for about a year now. I hadn't
stumbled across it until this spring,
but I've caught up. I've now listened to
every episode and really love what you
guys are doing. Not only because the
content is great, but it's really built
a nice community around people who are
living and breathing this stuff every
day.
As far as things go on my end, so you
can reach me, that's PhilG Carter on X.
You can also check out my website at
www.philgcarter.com.
And and then I'm launching a course with
Reforge in January, actually, on
consumer subscription growth. So as you
said, David, there was a lot to cover in
this podcast. And even with the time we
had, we only really scratched the
surface. And so if you feel like some of
these frameworks and tools we talked
about would be beneficial for your
business, reach out to me through the
channels that I mentioned. Or you can go
to reforge.com and you should be able to
find the course there as well. Awesome.
Phil, thanks so much. This was a blast.
And certainly in this hour and a half
already influenced my thinking a lot. So
I think it's going to be super valuable
for the audience. So thank you for
sharing today. Likewise. It was my
pleasure.
Thanks so much for listening.
If you have a minute, please leave a
review in your favorite podcast player.
You can also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.